Frederick T. Haneman Papers
Frederick T. Haneman Papers
1892-1914
Haneman, Frederick Theodore.
0.5 linear ft.
German-American physician and a prolific author and editor of both medical and general-interest papers and articles
2746538
Biographical History
Frederick Theodore Haneman (circa 1863-after 1940) was a German-American physician and a prolific author and editor of both medical and general-interest papers and articles.
According to the 1930 U.S. Census, Haneman was born in Prussia and came to the United States in 1888; he and his wife Laura, born in New York circa 1874, settled in New Jersey. Their surname is spelt "Hanemon" in the 1910 census. According to Haneman's own biographical statement, written in the third person and included in the collection, he spent "over 30 years on the editorial staff of Funk and Wagnalls Company as a writer for the Literary Digest, the several editions of the Standard Dictionary, the Jewish and Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedias, etc. He also was a collaborator to the latest edition of the International Encyclopedia, the Standard Encyclopedia of the Alcohol Problem, etc. For over ten years he was the editor of a well-known medical journal. During the war he was attached to the Belgian Relief...He is especially interested in sanitation and hygiene, education, history, and political science."
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frederick T. Haneman Papers consists of correspondence, medical material, memorabilia, and writings.
Correspondence consists almost entirely of letters from Haneman's wife Laura during a trip to Europe in 1913; some were sent from aboard ship, others from various locations in Europe. The majority of the letters are in German; typed transcripts, also in German and of unknown origin, are present for some of the letters. There is also one letter ro "My dear Son" from "Mother"; internal evidence suggests that the letter is from Laura Haneman to their son Vincent.
Medical material contains clippings and handwritten notes on various remedies for everything from asthma to impotence, and a set of four published papers on the medical and therapeutic uses of radium.
Memorabilia consists of a handwritten document, in German, regarding a coin collection; loose pages from a book entitled Erforschung der Erdrinde (labeled in English, "History of the Discovery of the Earth's Surface"), and three small diaries or daybooks with various sorts of material laid in. Volume 1 (volume numbers are not original but were assigned for identification purposes) includes 20 or so printed and hand-colored pages of coats of arms for various German cities.
Writings, most in English and most handwritten, consist of Haneman's own biographical statement and drafts of various articles and essays. Most were likely written for one of the encyclopedias to which he was a contributor. Topics include radium, sunbathing, alcohol, German history, and politics. Of particular interest is a letter to the editor of the New York Times, annotated as "unpublished," on "Causes of the European War" written in August 1914, less than a month after the outbreak of World War I.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged in alphabetical order by type or title, with the exception of correspondence which is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science and medicine; Haneman, Frederick Theodore.; Haneman, Laura.; Saubermann, Sigmund.; Alcoholism -- Study and teaching.; Alcoholism -- Germany.; Devices (Heraldry) -- Germany.; Drinking of alcoholic beverages -- Germany.; Drinking of alcoholic beverages -- Health aspects.; Europe -- Description and travel.; Germany -- History.; Medical care -- Germany --19th century.; Medical care -- United States --19th century.; Medicine -- Formulae, receipts, prescriptions.; Medicine, Naval.; Radium -- Therapeutic use.; Sun-baths.; Therapeutics -- History -- 19th century.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Causes.; Books.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Commonplace books.; Manuscripts for publication.; Drafts (documents); Postcards.; Physicians.; Editors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Vincent S. Haneman, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Laura's letters from Europe, 1913 (Box 1)
  - Mother, 1922 (Box 1)
- Medical material
  - Advertisements, Vapo-Cresolene, Kleanwell toothbrushes, more. (Box 1)
  - Book, Arzneiverordnungen zum Gebrauche für Klinicisten und practische Aerzte von Dr. S. Rabow, Professor an der Universität Lausanne [Drug regulations for the use of clinicians and practicing physicians, by Dr. S. Rabow, Professor at the University of Lausanne], 1892; inscribed and annotated by Haneman (Box 1)
  - Clippings, undated; medical remedies from books, newspapers, etc., in German and English (Box 1)
  - Notes, undated; handwritten notes and recipes for remedies, treatment, diagnosis, etc. (Box 1)
  - Papers on radium, 1912-1914; Radium Emanation Therapy with Radio-Rem, Radium Therapy Corporation (circa 1914);The Curative Action of Radium, Dr. Sigmund Saubermann (1914); Radium Emanation and Physiological Processes, Dr. Sigmund Saubermann (1912); An Address on the Progress of Radium-Therapy, Dr. Sigmund Saubermann (1912) (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Coin collection documentation ("Münzen = Sammlung"), undated; in German; includes hand-drawn family trees of various royal families (Box 1)
  - History of discovery of Earth's surface, undated; pages from a facsimile of a 17th century book, Erforschung der Erdrinde [Exploration of the Earth's crust] as well as a few interesting modern book pages with transparent overlays (Box 1)
  - [Volume 1], undated; handwritten quotations in German, English, Latin, Greek; laid in are 20 or so printed hand-colored pages of coats of arms for various German cities (Box 1)
  - [Volume 2], undated; handwritten quotations and other material in German, English, Latin, Greek (Box 1)
  - [Volume 3], undated; quotations, poetry, mostly in German (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Biographical statement, undated; handwritten (Box 1)
  - Causes of the European War, Aug 1914; handwritten letter to editor of New York Times, in both German and English (Box 1)
  - Germany [alcohol in], undated; draft, mostly handwritten with substantial edits, about 70 pages; statistics, including large tables of data; bibliography, typed; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Heliotherapeutics, undated; two handwritten drafts; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hesse, undated; short type-written history of the region (Box 1)
  - History of the Secret Tribunal..., undated; translation into English of the first 14 or so pages of Histoire Du Tribunal Secret D'après Les Loix Et Les Constitutions De L'empire Germanique by Jean Nicolas Etienne de Bock; typescript (Box 1)
  - Insanity and alcohol, undated; typescript (Box 1)
  - Mania a potu, undated; handwritten draft (Box 1)
  - Marine krieg chirurgie (misgebraucht) [Naval War Surgery (abuses of)], undated; handwritten draft, in German (Box 1)
  - Marriage and drink, undated; handwritten draft of article for Standard Encyclopedia of the Alcohol Problem; includes note to typist about formatting and invoice from typist (Box 1)
  - Miles, Nelson Appleton, undated; handwritten draft of biographical article on the United States army officer (Box 1)
  - Nature's drugstore, undated; handwritten draft (Box 1)
  - Radium and its use in medicine, undated; handwritten draft (Box 1)
  - Sunbathing, undated; handwritten draft (Box 1)
  - Fragments, miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)